all right
[Music]
theoretically bathing your muscles in an
alkaline environment should enable
faster acid removal from muscle cells
delaying the muscle fatigue the suit of
the buildup of lactic acid in the muscle
given these buffering effects no wonder
sodium bicarbonate in other words baking
soda has been found to have such
significant ergogenic or performance
enhancing effects on muscular endurance
the problem with loading with baking
soda is that it frequently causes severe
gastrointestinal distress and at
standard doses you could easily take in
twice the recommended upper daily limit
of sodium in just that one load
therefore what about a low acid diet
which focuses on high intakes of fruits
and vegetables that may be an attractive
alternative to bicarbonate loading for
improving anaerobic exercise performance
meaning short burst activity like
sprinting
today's diets are acid forming meaning
higher in animal foods with fewer
vegetables and fruits whereas in general
the alkaline promoting diet is centered
around whole plant foods with few
processed foods and Less meat Dairy and
eggs which are accepted as acid-forming
Foods although alkalizing chemicals such
as sodium bicarbonate have been shown to
consistently improve performance
alkalizing diets do not demonstrate the
same effect or review 10 studies that
investigate the effect of High versus
low dietary acid loads on athletic
performance did not find consistently
improved exercise performance at maximal
or sub-maximal exercise intensities
however maybe they just didn't go
alkaline enough for example in this
study they had people eat more fruits
and vegetables and Less meat cheese
cereals and eggs but saw no difference
in any performance related parameters
but a sufficiently alkaline diet is
characterized by the production of
alcohol and urine a pH of P at least
seven or higher if you look at what the
participants achieved most failed to
meet The Benchmark so their diet may
just not have been alkaline forming
enough
in this study showing enhanced 400 meter
sprint performance they were able to
swap out enough meat eggs cheese and
cereal products and swap in enough
fruits and vegetables that the word just
barely able to make seven and they did
get a little performance boost
suggesting that it's possible to improve
Sprint performance by consuming
alkalizing natural foods and beverages
without the ingestion of baking soda
thus an alkalizing diet may be an easy
and natural way to enhance performance
however the performance enhancement was
only about two percent just a few
seconds but check out this study same
general strategy more fruits and
vegetables unless the acid promoting
foods such as Meats cheeses and refined
grains but they weren't messing around
six to eight cups of vegetables plus
more than four servings of fruit a day
got their urine up over seven and a 21
performance enhancement that's
extraordinary
now this doesn't necessarily mean it has
anything to do with the pH I mean they
ate more vegetables which contain
dietary nitrates which alone acutely
improve exercise performance it's
possible that nitrates might have
enhanced exercise performance during the
low acid trial however that would entail
extracting more energy from every breath
and they didn't find that but anytime
you make huge changes in people's diets
it's hard to pinpoint exactly what made
the critical difference
but these extra benefits are a feature
not a bug because a more alkaline
forming diet is rich in fruits and
vegetables and deplete of many unhealthy
Foods a low acid diet can only provide
exercise performance benefits but might
also reduce chronic disease risk
any performance benefits in non-athletes
the effect of an alkaline diet on body
composition and aerobic exercise
performance of sedentary women a
randomized controlled trust swapping in
vegetable protein sources like legumes
for animal protein sources and
a greater decrease in weight body fat
Mass lactic acid accumulation and
perceived exertion levels all the while
exhibiting a boost in exercise
performance duration and VO2 max levels
which is a measure of Fitness again pH
could just be one of many explanations
why eating healthier could make you
perform better but either way we should
recommend athletes of all ages focus on
consuming ample amounts of fruits and
vegetables if only to maintain long-term
health
[Music]
thank you